We ask a lot of questions
about our diet.
What’s the right way to
treat a chronic illness?
Fight off a virus,
lose weight?
The problem is, we get
a lot of different answers.
Well, I’m here to help.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at
why hair turns gray,
what’s the role of genetics,
and what we can do about it.
The graying of hair is one of
the most obvious signs of aging.
It's also known by a technical
term that I had never heard of,
"canities."
The first time I saw the word,
I misread it,
wondering what gray hair
had to do with dentistry.
Evidently, gray hair
isn't really white,
but the pale yellowish tinge
of the constitutive
keratin protein,
but, like polar bears,
it just looks white by the way
light reflects off of it.
Why is hair pigmented
in the first place?
Some suggest it may be
for detoxification,
as natural toxins
like heavy metals
bind to the pigment melanin
to be excreted from the body
through hair outgrowth.
That's why you can estimate
the amount of fish consumption
from the mercury content
of children's hair clippings,
why "[a]nalysis of hair mercury
may be warranted
before pregnancy"
in women who eat a lot of fish,
and why the levels
of mercury in the hair
of those eating plant-based
diets were found to be
up to ten times lower than those
who just occasionally ate fish.
Within three months of switching
to a plant-based diet,
the levels of mercury, lead, and
cadmium growing out in your hair
appear to drop significantly
but build back up
when meat and eggs
are added back into the diet.
Enough with the science trivia.
What causes our hair
to turn gray,
and what can we do about it?
In medical school,
you learn about
the so-called 50-50-50 rule.
By the age of 50,
the dictum goes,
50 percent of the population
has at least 50 percent
gray hair.
But that was based on
a homogenous population
of largely white,
fair-haired Australians.
The global range is more like
6 percent to 23 percent
are 50 percent gray by 50.
Though not as memorable
an axiom,
it looks like 75 percent or so
of people 45 to 65 years old
have about 25 percent gray hair.
Those of African
or Asian descent
tend to show less gray hair.
White people generally start
to gray in their mid-30s,
Asians in their late 30s,
and Africans in their mid-40s,
such that premature graying
is defined
before 20 in Caucasians
but before 30
in African Americans.
Age 25 has been suggested
as a cutoff for India.
Premature or not,
what causes hair to turn gray
in the first place?
The hair follicle is
a complex little mini-organ
that anchors and grows
a single hair.
In the base of the follicle bulb
as few as 100
pigment-making cells
normally stain the emerging hair
shaft with melanin pigments
that can range in color
from black to red.
A single hair grows for about
3.5 years before falling out
and a new one starts
growing in its place.
So, graying may start
after about 10 hair cycles
when pigment deposition declines
as the pigment generating cells,
called melanocytes,
start to become depleted.
What kills them off?
There's a depigmentation
disorder called vitiligo
where melanocytes
in the skin are killed off
by the buildup
of hydrogen peroxide,
which can decompose
into toxic free radicals.
So, researchers checked,
and indeed,
the same "massive" levels were
found in aging hair follicles.
Where does the hydrogen peroxide
come from?
It's naturally generated as a
by-product of melanin synthesis,
but normally countered
by an antioxidant enzyme
called catalase.
The problem, it seems,
is that catalase
and other antioxidant defenses
may decline as we age
and leave melanocytes vulnerable
to their own hot potato
production of pigment.
Our own eyelashes present
"an enigma in plain sight."
Eyelashes tend to be the
darkest hairs on the human body
and undergo graying
significantly later
than other hairs.
The explanation appears to be
the presence of a particular
antioxidant protein
missing from regular hair,
consistent with the prevailing
"free radical
theory of graying."
Did you know that
vitamin B12 deficiency
is one of the rare reversible
causes of hair graying?
Here’s the story.
The graying of hair,
the age-related "exhaustion
of the pigmentary potential"
is thought to be mainly genetic,
with a family history
of premature graying
present in up to 90 percent
of cases.
But if the rate of graying
is caused by oxidative damage,
what role might be played
by antioxidants
and systemic oxidative stress
outside of the hair follicle?
Those with premature graying
do seem to have
higher circulating markers
of oxidative damage
and lower antioxidant levels
in blood.
The higher prevalence of
premature graying among smokers
also supports this possibility
that exogenous free radicals
may speed up the accumulation
of oxidative insults
in the aging hair follicle.
Obese individuals
also tend to gray early,
consistent with
the oxidative stress concept,
though drinkers do not.
Alcohol consumption clearly
causes oxidative stress
yet is not
significantly associated
with premature graying.
Those trying to maximize
their intake of antioxidants
by eating plant-based
must deal with
the Achilles heel-
the risk of
vitamin B12 deficiency
for those not actively
supplementing their diets
with B12,
whether from supplements
or fortified foods.
B12 deficiency is one
of the rare reversible causes
of hair graying through
some unknown mechanism.
Thankfully, hair can repigment
after B12 repletion.
Another reversible cause
is hypothyroidism,
which can be reversed with
thyroid hormone replacement.
Rather than oxidative stress,
what about regular stress?
Does fight-or-flight
turn hair white?
Marie Antoinette syndrome
refers to the rapid graying of
hair due to stress or trauma,
based on the (likely apocryphal)
story of her hair going
completely white
on the eve of her beheading.
Sporadic validated reports
of sudden graying
have been attributed
to the sudden diffuse loss
of pigmented hairs,
leaving the gray hairs behind,
offering the illusion
of transmogrification.
In mice, acute stressors
can lead to hair graying
via rapid depletion
of melanocyte stem cells,
perhaps because
psychological stress
may lead to oxidative stress
(based on cross-sectional
studies that link higher
perceived stress to higher
levels of oxidative DNA damage).
Why might we even have evolved
to turn gray
in response to stress?
Drawing on an analogy
from the authority afforded
silverback mountain gorillas,
stress-induced graying
may confer
a "school of hard knocks"
evolutionary advantage
for leadership.
For real-world consequences,
check out the results
of this study:
hospitalized patients
treated by gray-haired
attending physicians
were found to be
significantly more likely
to make it
out of the hospital alive
than those attended
by dark or blond-haired docs.
As a mark of age, gray hair may
also be a mark of experience.
But might having
gray hair yourself
increase your own chances
of ending up in the hospital?
Might premature
or extensive graying
be a sign of accelerated aging
and subsequent risk
of age-related diseases?
The data is mixed.
Some studies suggest
the degree of graying
is an independent risk factor
for coronary artery disease,
for example based on higher
coronary calcium scores
in grayer individuals.
However,
by far the largest study,
which followed 13,000
men and women for 16 years,
found no correlation
between graying
(or hair loss or wrinkles)
and overall mortality.
The only exception appeared
to be a small fraction of men
without any gray hair
(just 6 percent
of those in their 50s,
2 percent of those in their 60s,
and 1 percent
of those in their 70s),
who did seem to have a
significantly lower mortality.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you hear about any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest major book,
“How Not to Age” is out.
Check it out from your
local public library.
I also wrote a
mini book on Ozempic.
Available in softcover,
e-book, and audio versions.
Check it out on NutritionFacts.org.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.